Finding Aid for William Ratigan papers, 1939-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Ratigan papers 1939-1978
Ratigan, William.
3 linear feet
852122 Aa 2
Charlevoix, Michigan resident, novelist and historian of Great Lakes shipwrecks, the Mackinac Bridge, folklore, and other subjects; correspondence, manuscripts of books, and research materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of William Ratigan (donor no. 4671 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Ratigan was born in Detroit, Michigan. He attended the University of Detroit, 1931 and 1933, and graduated from the University of Tennessee Chattanooga in 1935. He later went back to college receiving his M.A. and Ph.D. from Michigan State University (1961 and 1963).
Ratigan began his career in the news division of NBC, first in Denver, then during World War Two as supervisor of NBC's war correspondents and commentators for the Pacific Theater.
A prolific writer, Ratigan was the author of several books, many of them on Michigan themes, including Great Lakes shipwrecks, the Mackinac Bridge, Michigan folklore, the building of the Soo Canal among others. Much of his career, after leaving NBC, was devoted to his literary endeavors as a writer and publisher.
The William Ratigan collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts of his books, research and reference files on topics of interest to him, and photographs. There are letters in the collection from William B. Eerdmans, Marianne Moore, Milo Quaife, David B. Steinman, and folklorist Ivan Walton.
The photographs in the collection are of shipping and boating at Charlevoix, Michigan, of Charlevoix boat builder, Roy Ranger, of construction of the Mackinac Bridge, of the Sault Sainte Marie Canal, and of other topics related to Ratigan's writing interests.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Charlevoix (Mich.); Folklore--Michigan.; Great Lakes (North America); Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Ratigan, William.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Boat and ship industry.; Boats.; Bridges--Michigan--Mackinac, Straits of.; Charlevoix (Mich.); Fish.; Illinois (Ship); Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Mackinac, Straits of (Mich.)--Bridges.; Ranger, Roy.; Ratigan, William.; Sault Sainte Marie Canal (Mich.); Ships--Great Lakes.
Contributors:
Arnold, Jennie Waterman.; Eerdmans, William B.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Quaife, Milo Milton, 1880-1959.; Steinman, D. B. (David Barnard), 1886-1960.; Walton, Ivan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1939-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
    (include letter from Milo Quaife, July 19, 1954)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (include letter from Marianne Moore, March 27, 1958 also letter from David Steinman)
  - 1959 (Box 1)
    (include letter from David Steinman)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    (include letter from David Steinman, January 6, 1960; also letter from Ivan Walton, April 10, 1961)
  - 1970-1978 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts to books
  - Soo Canal, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Soo Canal and Song of Hiawatha (Box 1)
  - Hiawatha and America's Mightiest Mile (Box 1)
  - The Adventures of Captain McCargo, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Straits of Mackinac, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Highways over Broad Water (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Shipwrecks and Survivals, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - The Long Crossing (Box 2)
  - Tiny Tim Pine, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - The Adventures of Paul Bunyan and Babe (Box 2)
  - The Blue Snow (Box 2)
  - Two Men in a Rowboat (Box 2)
- Research and Reference Files
  - Great Lakes History, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Mackinac Bridge and David B. Steinman, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Soo Locks and Charles T. Harvey (Box 2)
  - Shipwreck of the "Carl D. Bradley" 1958 (Box 2)
  - Shipwreck of the "Edmund Fitzgerald" 1975 (Box 3)
  - Year-Round Shipping on the Great Lakes (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes Shipwrecks (Box 3)
  - Autobiography 1958 of Jennie Arnold of Traverse City (Box 3)
  - Michigan State Library and Esther Loughin (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes Publishing Company (Box 3)
  - Artists (Box 3)
- Other materials
  - Reviews and Publicity for Ratigan's Books (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Book Theories of Counseling, edited by Buford Stefflre and W. Harold Grant, includes "Counseling Theory and Practice in the School", by William Ratigan (Box 3)
  - Book Deep Water, by Eleanor Ratigan (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous books and pamphlets (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Charlevoix area (Box 3)
  - Fish (Box 3)
  - Mackinac Bridge construction and dedication (Box 3)
  - Ranger, Roy, Charlevoix boat builder (Box 3)
  - Ratigan and friends (Box 3)
    (including ice boat)
  - Sault Ste. Marie Canal (Box 3)
  - Ships
    - Illinois grounded south of Charlevoix breakwater August 1906 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)